Finding aid for the Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Կարօ Մինասեան հայկական հավաքածու LSC.1632
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Books: Գրքեր, 1756-1963; Series 15.
  - George Mackertich: Գէորգ Մկրտիչեան, 1900-1932; Subseries 15.2.
    This subseries contains handwritten and published books belonging to George Mackertich. Of note are his notes and speeches in Armenian and English given at meetings of the British and Foreign Bible Society. Materials are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Գէորգ Մկրտիչեանին պատկանող ձեռագրուած եւ հրատարակուած գրքեր: Նշանակալից են իր հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով ծանօթագրութի ւններ եւ Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութեան հանդիպումներ ուն արջեւ ներկայացուած խօսքեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - British and Foreign Bible Society: Manual of the Bible Colporteur: Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութիւն՝ Աստուածաշնչի շրջուն վաճառորդի ձեռագիրք, circa 1920s (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Questions on the First Epistle to Timothy: Հարցումներ վասն Առաջինթղթին առ Տիմոթէոս, circa 1920s (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - The Mysterious Parcel: Խորհրդաւոր կապոցը, circa 1920s (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - British and Foreign Bible Society: Notes and Speeches: Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութիւն՝ ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ խօսքեր, 1927-1928 (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - British and Foreign Bible Society: Notes and Speeches: Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութիւն՝ ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ խօսքեր, 1928 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - British and Foreign Bible Society: Notes and Speeches: Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութիւն՝ ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ խօսքեր, 1928 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - British and Foreign Bible Society: Notes and Speeches: Բրիտանոյ եւ Արտաքին Աստուածաշնչի Ընկերութիւն՝ ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ խօսքեր, 1929 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - Daily Readings of the Holy Scriptures (Beirut): Սուրբ Գրոց առօրեա ընթերցումներ (Պեյրութ), 1932 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Religious: Կրօնական, 1756-1933; Subseries 15.3.
    This subseries contains books of a mostly religious nature, including sermons, prayer books, liturgical books, and others. Most of the books are handwritten, and some copied from published books. Notable items are the Outline of Bahai Teaching, the Number and Inventory of Armenian Inhabitants of Calcutta, and the books of musical notation. Materials are in Armenian and English.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է յատկապէս կրօնական գրքեր, ներառեալ քարոզներ, աղօթագրքեր, ծիսական գրքեր, եւ այլն: Մեծ մասամբ ձեռագրուած են, մի զգալի մաս հրատարակուած գրքերից օրինակուած: Նշանակալից են՝ Ուրուագիծ Պահայական վարդապետութե ան, Թիւ եւ ցուցակ հայկազնեայց բնակելոց ի կալկաթոյ, եւ երաժշտական գրքեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Sermons on John 3:16 and Luke 11:5-13: Քարոզներ՝ Յովհ. Գ. 16 եւ Ղուկ. ԺԱ. 5-13, 19th century (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript: Ձեռագիր, 1756 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - School Prayers: Դպրոցական Աղօթքներ (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - Musical Notation of Mass by Priest K.V. Kirakosean (New Julfa): Պատարագի ձայնագրութիւն՝ տիրացու Կ.Վ. Կիրակոսեան (Նոր Ջուղայ) (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Book that is called "Equal book," which is meditations of times past and present (Step'anos Yerets'I, 1787) (copied in 1947), vol 1: Գիրք որ կոչի հանգիտագիրք որ է մտածմունք ժամանակակից անցելոց եւ ներկայից (Ստեփանոս երեցի, 1787, օրինակուած 1947- ին) հատ Ա (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Book that is called "Equal book," which is meditations of times past and present (Step'anos Yerets'I, 1787) (copied in 1947), vol 2: Գիրք որ կոչի հանգիտագիրք որ է մտածմունք ժամանակակից անցելոց եւ ներկայից (Ստեփանոս երեցի, 1787, օրինակուած 1947- ին) հատ Բ (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Order of Worship for Sunday School: Կանոն կիրակնօրեայ դպրոցի պաշտաման, 19th century (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Armenian prayer book: Աղօթագիրք, 1926 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - From Ter Dionesius's Archive: Տէր Դիոնէսիուսի արխիւից, 18--? (Box 49, Folder 18)
    - Prosopopoeia of the four ends (Mkrtich' Awgerean, 1810, copied in 1832): Դիմառնութիւն չորից վերջնոց (Մկրտիչ Աւգերեան, 1810, օրինակուած 1832- ին) (Box 49, Folder 19)
    - Theological Discourses (Harut'iwn Sahakean Aghanut'eants'): Աստւածաբանական բանք (Յարութիւն Սահակեան Աղանութեանց), 1840-1841 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    - Notes and Scriptural Quotations concerning God and Theology: Աստուծոյ եւ աստուածաբանութեան մասին ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ Աստուածաշնչի մէջբերումներ (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Number and inventory of Armenian inhabitants in the capital city of Calcutta (includes various announcements): Թիւ եւ ցուցակ հայկազնեայց բնակելոց ի մայրաքաղաքիս կալկաթոյ (ներառեալ զանազան ծանուցումներ), 1868 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Priest's Book of Holy Minas Church: Քահանայագիրք Սուրբ Մինաս Եկեղեցւոյ, 1928 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - The Longevous Eznik Vardapetean and his life and work, 1900-1922, Peria-Julfa-Hamadan (H.K. Barseghean): Երկարակեցեան Եզնիկ Վարդապետեան եւ իր կեանք ու գործը 1900-1922. Փերիա- Ջուղա-Համադան (Յ.Ք. Բարսեղեան), 1933 (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Alphabetical word list: Այբուբենի կարգով բառերի ցանկ, No dates (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Defense of the Armenian Catholic and Apostolic Holy Church in response to the See of St. Peter: Պաշտպանութիւն Հայաստանեայց կաթուղիկէ եւ առաքելական ս. եկեղեցւոյ ի պատասխանի աթոռ ս. Պետրոսի Առաքելապետի անուանեալ գրոցն, after 1854 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - The Passions of the Savior: Գործք չարչարանց փրկչին, 1863 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - The Pearl of the Kingdom of Heaven: Brief Lessons on the teaching of Jesus: Մարգարիտ արքայութեան երկնից Յիսուսի վարդապետութեան համառօտ դասեր, after 1876 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Commentary on the Four Gospels with a harmonization table: Մեկնոթիւն չորից Աւետարանաց հանդերձ տախտակաւ համաձայնութեան, 1888 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Armenian music scores for church: Հայկական եկեղեցական երաժշտական նօթաշար, 1892 (Box 50, Folder 6)
      Includes sketches of manuscript paintings in pencil
    - Armenian music scores for church (and a note from K. V. Ter Kirakosean): Հայկական երաժշտական նօթաշար եկեղեցու համար (եւ ծանուցագիր Կ.Վ. Տէր Կիրակօսեան), 1892 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Outline of Baha'i Teaching: Ուրուագիծ Պահայական վարդապետութեան, 1921 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Christian Instructions and other Prayers in the common language: Աշխարհաբար քրիստոնեական կրթութիւնք եւ այլ աղօթք, 1926 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - History: Պատմութիւն, 1812-1949; Subseries 15.4.
    This subseries contains historical books and writings, some published, some handwritten. Notable is the Ethnography of the province of Charmahal, and the chronicle of New Julfa (incomplete). Materials are in Armenian, Russian, and French. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում էթէ՛ ձեռագրուածթէ ՛ հրատարակուած պատմական գրքեր եւ գրութիւններ: Նշանակալից են Չհարմահալ գաւառի ազգագրութիւն ը եւ Նոր Ջուղայի ժամանակագրու թիւնը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, ռուսերէնով, եւ ֆրանսերէնով են:
    - Copies of early 19th-century documents: 19-րդ դարու փաստաթղթերի օրինակներ (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Armenian Volunteers: Հայ կամաւորներ, 1916 (Box 50, Folder 14)
    - Catalog of books of the New Julfan Association Library preserving a cultural tie with Soviet Armenia: Սովետական Հայաստանի հետ կուլտուրական կապ պահպանող Նոր-Ջուղայի հայկական ընկերութեան գրադարանի գրքերի ցուցակների, 1946 (Box 50, Folder 15)
    - Chronicle of New Julfa (1860-1947): Ժամանակագրութիւն Նոր- Ջուղայու (1860-1947) (Box 50, Folder 16)
    - Ethnography of the Iranian Province of Charmahal (Aw. Priest Yedgarean): Իրանի Չհարմահալ գաւառը, ազգագրութիւն (Աւ. Քահ. Եդգարեան), 1949 (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - Dictionaries: Բառարաններ, 1873-1963; Subseries 15.5.
    This subseries contains several handwritten and one typed dictionary. Notable is the Armenian- Indonesian handwritten dictionary, and the typed Dictionary of the New Julfan dialect. Materials are in Armenian, English, and Indonesian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի քանի ձեռագրուած եւ մի մեքենագրուած բառարան: Նշանակալից են Հայերէնից Ինդոնէզերէն ձեռագրուած բառարանը եւ մեքենագրուած Նոր Ջուղայի բարբառի բառարանը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ Ինդոնէզերէնո վ են:
    - Armenian dictionary: Հայերէնի բառարան, 1873 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Armenian-English Dictionary: Հայերէնից Անգլերէն բառարան, 1918 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Dictionary of the New Julfan Dialect (Vagharshak Tēr Sukeasean): Բառարան Նոր- Ջուղայի բարբառի (Վաղարշակ Տէր Սուքեասեան), 1963 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Հայերէնից Ինդոնէզերէն բառարան: Armenian to Indonesian dictionary, undated (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - English-Armenian dictionary: Անգլերէնից Հայերէն բառարան, undated (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Medicine and Science: Բժշկութիւն եւ գիտութիւն, 1793-20th century; Subseries 15.6.
    This subseries contains typed and handwritten books and copies of books related to medicine and science. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է բժշկութեան եւ գիտութեան վերաբերող մեքենագրուած եւ ձեռագրուած գրքեր եւ գրքերի օրինակներ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Brief Medicine Book (with dictionary) by Doctor Hohannēs of Julfa: Բջշկական համառօտ (եւ բառարան) (բժիշկ Ջուղայեցի Յոհաննէս), 1793 (Box 51, Folder 6)
      It is a copy of the original (without illustrations)
    - Classification of Plants: Բույսերի կարգաբանութիւն, No date (Box 51, Folder 7)
      A handwritten translation of Grossgeims work in Russian on plant systems
    - Medical remedies: Բժշկական դարման, No date (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Medical textbook (with illustrations): Բժշկական դասագիրք (նկարներով), No date (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Mathematics: Թուաբանութիւն, Subseries 15.7.
    This subseries contains two mathematics textbooks in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է հայերէնով երկութուաբան ութիւն դասագրքեր:
    - Arithmetic book: Թուաբանութիւն գիրք, 1878 (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Math Copybook and Textbook for Armenian College: Թուաբանութիւն գիրք ի պետս Ազգային վարժարանաց (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Literature: Գրականութիւն, 1850-1959; Subseries 15.8.
    This vast subseries contains mostly handwritten books of literature and copies of books. A large portion are in verse. Notable is the large collection of Mōllay Nasrētin tales and the unpublished material. The books are in Armenian, with some English and Persian. Այս մեծածաւալ ենթակարգը պարունակում է մեծ մասամբ ձեռագրուած գրքեր եւ գրքերի օրինակներ: Մի զգալի մաս չափածոյ են: Նշանակալից է Մօլլայ Նասրէդինի պատմուածքների մեծ հաւաքածոյ եւ չհրատարակուա ծ նիւթեր: Գիրքերը հայերէնով են, մի քիչ անգլերէնով եւ պարսկերէնով:
    - Minstrel Composition (1830-1869): Աշուղական շարադրութիւն (1830-1869), 1951 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      Ghul Hovhannes (1830) and Ter Karapet (1869), Martiros Manukean, recorded by Ayvaz Vart'avanean.
    - The Conclusion of the world-ruining War and the most severe famine in Iran (1917-1918): Աշխարհաւեր պատերազմի հետեւանքը եւ ամենադաժան սովը Պարսկաստանում (1917-1918), 1920 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - The Political State of Iran on the occasion of the World War (1914-1918): Համաշխարհային պատերազմի առթիվ պարսկա- քաղաքական հանգամանք (1914-1918), 1920 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - The Darwinian Illusion and the unenviable educational state of New Julfa: Դարվինական ցնորք եւ կրթական աննախանձելի վիճակ ջուղայու, 1922 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Description of the heavenly bounties of the Creator for the enjoyment of his Creatures: Նկարագիր երկնապարգեւ բարեաց Արարչին ի վայելս ստեղծուածւոց իւրոց, 1922 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Oleaster and the merciless wealthy ones infatuated with money: Փշատ եւ անողորմ մեծատուններ արծաթի սիրամոլներ, 1924 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Vartan Stepanian, designer, painter: Վարդան Ստեփանեան՝ գծագրիչ, նկարիչ, 1948 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - From Charmahal Province, which was the place of my birth: Չարմահալ գաւառեն զի վասն քան գիւղից ծննդավայրս (?), 1950 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Mr Khach'atur Fak'ari's song book: Պրն. Խաչատուր Ֆաքարիի երգերի գիրք, 1951 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Collection of poetry (for Minas Abgarean from Mr. Suk'eas Tēr Sukesean): Ոտանաւորների հաւաքածոյ (Պարոն Սուքեաս Տէր Սուքեսեանից Մինաս Աբգարեանին), 1953 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Armenian translation of Shakespeare's Comdy of Errors: Շէքսպիրի Սխալների կատաերգութիւնը (թարգմանութիւն), 1954 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Collection of songs and poems: Երգերի եւ ոտանաւորների հաւաքածոյ, 1863 (Box 52, Folder 2)
      by Sargis Varterean(?)
    - Anecdotes (various): Պատմուածքներ (զանազան), 1959 (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - Armenian translation of Shakespeare's Comedy of Errors, Act II-V: Շէքսպիրի Սխալների կատակերգութիւնը (թարգմանութիւն), Գործողութիւն Բ-Ե, No date (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - Collection of Armenian Revolutionary poems: Հայկական յեղափոխական ոտանաւորների հաւաքածոյ, No date (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Collection of Mōllay Nasrēdin's stories and other folk tales: Մօլլայ Նասրէդինի պատմուածքների եւ այլ ժողովրդական պատմութիւնների հաւաքածոյ, No date (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - The pitiless horse: Անգութ երասխ, 1885 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - The grandson of Balaam's Donkey: Բաղաամու իշիթոռն, 1894 (Box 52, Folder 4)
      Instructive poetic tale about how the New Julfa Armenians have morally fallen.
    - The rich man and poor man: Մեծատունն եւ Աղքատն, 1895 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Translation of Shakespeare's Comedy of Errors into Armenian: Շէքսպիրի Սխալութիւնների կատակերգութիւն (թարգմանւած հայերենի), 1898 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Vigil (play): Հսկումը (թատրոն), 1902 (Box 52, Folder 7)
      Persian inscriptions in the back indicate that this play was translated to Persian and it was authorized to play.
    - The sounds of blood (N. Pōghoschanean): Արեան ձայները (Ն. Պօղոսճանեան), 1907 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Pepo: Պէպօ, 1918 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Ergaran: Երգարան, No date (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Miscellany of riddles and songs in Armenian, English, Persian: Զանազան հանելուկներ եւ երգեր հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, պարսկերէնով, No date (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - 15.9 Social Life: Ընկերային կեանք, 1858
    This subseries contains a published book concerning the conflict between H. Zohrabean and Bishop T'addēos. The book is in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի հրատարակուած գիրք Յ. Զոհրաբեանի եւ Թադդէոս Եպիսկոպոսի միջեւ վէճի մասին: Գիրքը հայերէնով է:
    - Book concerning the conflict between H. Zohrabean and Bishop T'addēos: Յ. Զոհրաբեանի եւ Թադդէոս Եպիսկոպոսի միջեւ վէճի վերաբեող գրութիւն, 1858 (Box 53, Folder 3)
- Martin Sarkies Free Mason Materials: Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանի մասոնական նիւթեր, 1889-1952; Series 16.
  This series contains Free Mason materials belonging to Martin Sarkies. The materials include garments and relics used in Masonic ritual, and a few documents and a book pertaining to Free masonry and Martin Sarkies. The materials are in English.
  Այս կարգը պարունակում է Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանին պատկանող մասոնական նիւթեր, ներառեալ հագուստներ եւ մասոնքներ մասոնական ծէս կատարելու համար, եւ Մասոնութեան եւ Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանին պատկանող մի քանի փաստաթղթեր եւ մի գիրք: Նիւթերը անգլերէնով են:
  - Free Mason garments, relics: Մասոանկան հագուստներ, մասունքներ, 1887-1952; Subseries 16.1.
    This subseries contains a few garments and relics used in Masonic ritual. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է մի քանի հագուստներ եւ մասունքներ մասոնական ծէս կատարելու համար:
    - Apron with matching shawl (in color and design): Գոգնոց իր հետ համընկնող զարդերով վզկապով, ca. 1887-1889 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Free Mason's green and white apron: Ազատ Մասոնական կանաչ եւ սպիտակ գոգնոց, ca. 1887-1889 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Shawl (stole): Վզկապ (փորուրար), ca. 1887-1889 (Box 55, Folder 3)
      A blue and Pink color shawl (stole) with a gold braded Free Mason triangle sign sewn on it
  - Free Mason documents and books: Ազատ մասոնական փաստաթղթեր եւ գրքեր, Subseries 16.2.
    This subseries contains a few documents and one book pertaining to Free Masonry and Martin Sarkies.
    Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Մասոնութեան եւ Մարտիրոս Սարգիսեանին վերաբերող մի քանի փաստաթղթեր եւ մի գիրք:
    - Book: Գիրք, 1895 (Box 55, Folder 4)
      The whole of craft Free-Masonry; A book by BR. G. Claret; Published in London
    - ITNOTGAOTU: Մասոն, Apri 10, 1889 (Box 55, Folder 5)
      The Supreme Grand and Royal Chapter of Royal Arch Masons of England; a cerificate given to Martin Sarkies.
    - United Grand Lodge of Ancient Free and Accepted Masons of England: Մասոններ Անգլիայում, February 8, 1888 (Box 55, Folder 6)
      Certifies that Martin Sarkies was received into Free- Masonry on 7th June 1887
    - Martin Sarkies Biographical note: Մարտին Սարգիսի կենսագրական ծանուցագիր, May, 1952 (Box 55, Folder 7)
      Obituary, by Dr. Caro Minasian
- Maps: Քարտէզներ, 1751-1930s; Series 17.
  This series contains maps of Armenia as well as other parts of the world. Notable is the "Map of Armenia according to ancient and recent geographers," the first printed map of Armenia.
  Այս կարգը պարունակում է Հայաստանի եւ աշխարհի այլ մասերին: Նշանակալից է Աշխարհացոյց Հայաստանեայց ըստ հին եւ նոր աշխարհագրաց Հայաստանի առաջին տպուած քարտէզը:
  - Maps of Armenia: Հայաստանի քարտէզներ, 1751-1900s; Subseries 17.1.
    This subseries contains three maps of Armenia. Notable is the "Map of Armenia according to ancient and recent geographers," the first printed map of Armenia, created by the Mekhitarist Congregation in Venice. The maps are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայաստանի երեք քարտեզներ: Նշանակալից է Աշխարհացոյց Հայաստանեայց ըստ հին եւ նոր աշխարհագրաց Հայաստանի առաջին տպուած քարտէզի Մխիթարեաններ ի կողմէն (Վենետիկ): Քարտէզները հայերէնով են:
    - Map of Armenia according to ancient and recent geographers (Venice) and other maps: Աշխարհացոյց Հայաստանեայց ըստ հին եւ նոր աշխարհագրաց (Վենետիկ) եւ այլ քարտէզներ, 1751-1900s (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - War map: Պատերազմական քարտէզ, Subseries 17.2.
    This subseries contains one map in Russian regarding war with Turkey. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Թուրքիոյ հետ պատերազմին վերաբերող մի քարտէզ ռուսերէնով:
    - Karta teatra Voiny c' Turtsieiu v' Evrop' Azin in na Chernom' Mor', undated (Box 54, Folder 2)
      Map of war with Turkey
  - Other Maps: Այլ քարտէզներ, Subseries 17.3.
    This subseries contains maps of Persia, South East Asia, and the Middle East. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Պարսկաստանի, Հարաւ Արեւելեան Ասիայի եւ Միջին Արեւելքի քարտէզներ:
    - Plan of Sourabaya with map of Java: Ջաւա, Սուրաբաեայի պլանով (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Bartholomew's map of the Middle East, colored to show height of land: Բարթօղեմիոսի Միջին Արեւելքի բարձրութիւններ ցուցադրող գունաւորուած քարտէզ (Box 57, Folder 5)
      English; "The Edinburgh Geographical Institute"; on the cover "Bartholomew's World Survery Series, Middle East: Turkey, Syria, Mesopotamia, Persia etc.